<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
 <!--
   Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
  contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
  this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
  The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
  (the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
  the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

       http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

   Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
   distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
   WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
   See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
   limitations under the License.
  -->
<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Configuration</title>
  <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<!--
<section name="Introduction">
<p>TODO: add section about tomcat configuration and avoiding the resource leak when reloading tomcat webapps.</p>
</section>
-->

<!--
<section name="Dynamic Properties">
maxTotal
maxIdle
minIdle
maxWaitMillis
testOnBorrow
testOnReturn
timeBetweenEvictionRunsMillis
numTestsPerEvictionRun
minEvictableIdleTimeMillis
testWhileIdle

</section>
-->

<section name="Parameters">

<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Description</th></hr>
<tr>
   <td>username</td>
   <td>The connection username to be passed to our JDBC driver to establish a connection.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>password</td>
   <td>The connection password to be passed to our JDBC driver to establish a connection.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>url</td>
   <td>The connection URL to be passed to our JDBC driver to establish a connection.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>driverClassName</td>
   <td>The fully qualified Java class name of the JDBC driver to be used.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>connectionProperties</td>
   <td>The connection properties that will be sent to our JDBC driver when establishing new connections.
       <br/>Format of the string must be [propertyName=property;]*
       <br/><strong>NOTE</strong> - The "user" and "password" properties will be passed explicitly, 
       so they do not need to be included here.
   </td>
</tr>
</table>


<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr>
<tr>
   <td>defaultAutoCommit</td>
   <td>driver default</td>
   <td>The default auto-commit state of connections created by this pool.
       If not set then the setAutoCommit method will not be called.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>defaultReadOnly</td>
   <td>driver default</td>
   <td>The default read-only state of connections created by this pool.
       If not set then the setReadOnly method will not be called.
       (Some drivers don't support read only mode, ex: Informix)
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>defaultTransactionIsolation</td>
   <td>driver default</td>
   <td>The default TransactionIsolation state of connections created by this pool.
       One of the following: (see 
       <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/1.4.2/docs/api/java/sql/Connection.html#field_summary">javadoc</a>)
       <ul>
          <li>NONE</li>
          <li>READ_COMMITTED</li>
          <li>READ_UNCOMMITTED</li>
          <li>REPEATABLE_READ</li>
          <li>SERIALIZABLE</li>
       </ul>
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>defaultCatalog</td>
   <td></td>
   <td>The default catalog of connections created by this pool.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
  <td>cacheState</td>
  <td>true</td>
  <td>If true, the pooled connection will cache the current readOnly and
      autoCommit settings when first read or written and on all subsequent
      writes. This removes the need for additional database queries for any
      further calls to the getter. If the underlying connection is accessed
      directly and the readOnly and/or autoCommit settings changed the cached
      values will not reflect the current state. In this case, caching should be
      disabled by setting this attribute to false.</td>
</tr>
</table>


<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr>
<tr>
   <td>initialSize</td>
   <td>0</td>
   <td>
      The initial number of connections that are created when the pool
      is started.
      <br/>Since: 1.2
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>maxTotal</td>
   <td>8</td>
   <td>
      The maximum number of active connections that can be allocated from
      this pool at the same time, or negative for no limit.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>maxIdle</td>
   <td>8</td>
   <td>
      The maximum number of connections that can remain idle in the
      pool, without extra ones being released, or negative for no limit.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>minIdle</td>
   <td>0</td>
   <td>
      The minimum number of connections that can remain idle in the
      pool, without extra ones being created, or zero to create none.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>maxWaitMillis</td>
   <td>indefinitely</td>
   <td>
      The maximum number of milliseconds that the pool will wait (when there
      are no available connections) for a connection to be returned before
      throwing an exception, or -1 to wait indefinitely.
   </td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_warning_sml.gif"/>
<strong>NOTE</strong>: If maxIdle is set too low on heavily loaded systems it is
possible you will see connections being closed and almost immediately new
connections being opened. This is a result of the active threads momentarily
closing connections faster than they are opening them, causing the number of
idle connections to rise above maxIdle. The best value for maxIdle for heavily
loaded system will vary but the default is a good starting point.
</p>


<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr>
<tr>
   <td>validationQuery</td>
   <td></td>
   <td>
The SQL query that will be used to validate connections from this pool
before returning them to the caller.  If specified, this query
<strong>MUST</strong> be an SQL SELECT statement that returns at least
one row. If not specified, connections will be validation by calling the
isValid() method.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>testOnCreate</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>
      The indication of whether objects will be validated after creation. If the
      object fails to validate, the borrow attempt that triggered the object
      creation will fail.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>testOnBorrow</td>
   <td>true</td>
   <td>
      The indication of whether objects will be validated before being
      borrowed from the pool.  If the object fails to validate, it will be
      dropped from the pool, and we will attempt to borrow another.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>testOnReturn</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>
      The indication of whether objects will be validated before being
      returned to the pool.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>testWhileIdle</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>
      The indication of whether objects will be validated by the idle object
      evictor (if any).  If an object fails to validate, it will be dropped
      from the pool.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>timeBetweenEvictionRunsMillis</td>
   <td>-1</td>
   <td>
      The number of milliseconds to sleep between runs of the idle object
      evictor thread.  When non-positive, no idle object evictor thread will
      be run.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>numTestsPerEvictionRun</td>
   <td>3</td>
   <td>
      The number of objects to examine during each run of the idle object
      evictor thread (if any).
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>minEvictableIdleTimeMillis</td>
   <td>1000 * 60 * 30</td>
   <td>
      The minimum amount of time an object may sit idle in the pool before it
      is eligable for eviction by the idle object evictor (if any).
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>softMiniEvictableIdleTimeMillis</td>
   <td>-1</td>
   <td>
      The minimum amount of time a connection may sit idle in the pool before
      it is eligible for eviction by the idle connection evictor, with
      the extra condition that at least "minIdle" connections remain in the
      pool. When miniEvictableIdleTimeMillis is set to a positive value,
      miniEvictableIdleTimeMillis is examined first by the idle 
      connection evictor - i.e. when idle connections are visited by the
      evictor, idle time is first compared against miniEvictableIdleTimeMillis
      (without considering the number of idle connections in the pool) and then
      against softMinEvictableIdleTimeMillis, including the minIdle constraint.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>maxConnLifetimeMillis</td>
   <td>-1</td>
   <td>
      The maximum lifetime in milliseconds of a connection. After this time is
      exceeded the connection will fail the next activation, passivation or
      validation test. A value of zero or less means the connection has an
      infinite lifetime.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>connectionInitSqls</td>
   <td>null</td>
   <td>
      A Collection of SQL statements that will be used to initialize physical 
      connections when they are first created.  These statements are executed
      only once - when the configured connection factory creates the connection.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>lifo</td>
   <td>true</td>
   <td>
      True means that borrowObject returns the most recently used ("last in")
      connection in the pool (if there are idle connections available).  False
      means that the pool behaves as a FIFO queue - connections are taken from
      the idle instance pool in the order that they are returned to the pool.
   </td>
</tr>
</table>

<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr><tr>
   <td>poolPreparedStatements</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>Enable prepared statement pooling for this pool.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>maxOpenPreparedStatements</td>
   <td>unlimited</td>
   <td>
      The maximum number of open statements that can be allocated from
      the statement pool at the same time, or negative for no limit.
   </td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_info_sml.gif"/>
This component has also the ability to pool PreparedStatements.
When enabled a statement pool will be created for each Connection
and PreparedStatements created by one of the following methods will be pooled:
<ul>
   <li>public PreparedStatement prepareStatement(String sql)</li>
   <li>public PreparedStatement prepareStatement(String sql, int resultSetType, int resultSetConcurrency)</li>
</ul>
</p>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_warning_sml.gif"/>
<strong>NOTE</strong> - Make sure your connection has some resources left for the other statements.
Pooling PreparedStatements may keep their cursors open in the database, causing a connection to run out of cursors,
especially if maxOpenPreparedStatements is left at the default (unlimited) and an application opens a large number
of different PreparedStatements per connection. To avoid this problem, maxOpenPreparedStatements should be set to a
value less than the maximum number of cursors that can be open on a Connection.
</p>


<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr><tr>
   <td>accessToUnderlyingConnectionAllowed</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>Controls if the PoolGuard allows access to the underlying connection.</td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>When allowed you can access the underlying connection using the following construct:</p>
<source>
    Connection conn = ds.getConnection();
    Connection dconn = ((DelegatingConnection) conn).getInnermostDelegate();
    ...
    conn.close()
</source>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_info_sml.gif"/>
Default is false, it is a potential dangerous operation and misbehaving programs can do harmfull things. (closing the underlying or continue using it when the guarded connection is already closed)
Be carefull and only use when you need direct access to driver specific extentions.
</p>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_warning_sml.gif"/>
<b>NOTE:</b> Do not close the underlying connection, only the original one.
</p>


<table>
<hr><th>Parameter</th><th>Default</th><th>Description</th></hr>
<tr>
   <td>removeAbandoned</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>
      Flag to remove abandoned connections if they exceed the
      removeAbandonedTimout.<br/>
      If set to true a connection is considered abandoned and eligible
      for removal if it has not been used for longer than the removeAbandonedTimeout.<br/>
      Creating a Statement, PreparedStatement or CallableStatement or using
      one of these to execute a query (using one of the execute methods)
      resets the lastUsed property of the parent connection.<br/>
      Setting this to true can recover db connections from poorly written
      applications which fail to close a connection.
   </td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>removeAbandonedTimeout</td>
   <td>300</td>
   <td>Timeout in seconds before an abandoned connection can be removed.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
   <td>logAbandoned</td>
   <td>false</td>
   <td>
      Flag to log stack traces for application code which abandoned
      a Statement or Connection.<br/>
      Logging of abandoned Statements and Connections adds overhead
      for every Connection open or new Statement because a stack   
      trace has to be generated.  
   </td>
</tr>
</table>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_info_sml.gif"/>
If you have enabled "removeAbandoned" then it is possible that a connection is reclaimed by the pool because
it is considered to be abandoned. This mechanism is triggered when (getNumIdle() &lt; 2) and
(getNumActive() &gt; getMaxTotal() - 3)
</p>
<p>
<img src="images/icon_info_sml.gif"/>
For example, maxTotal=20 and 18 active connections and 1 idle connection would trigger the "removeAbandoned".
But only the active connections that aren't used for more then "removeAbandonedTimeout" seconds are removed,
default (300 sec). Traversing a resultset doesn't count as being used. Creating a Statement, PreparedStatement
or CallableStatement or using one of these to execute a query (using one of the execute methods) resets
the lastUsed property of the parent connection.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
